Guide to the Dial/Scofield Thayer Papers: Addition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dial/Scofield Thayer papers: addition
1885-1928
YCAL MSS 95
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(5 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence and personal papers of Scofield Thayer, including letters from Amy and Robert von Erdberg, Erik von Jurié, R. T. Nichol, and Florence Thayer. Personal papers include school compositions and other writings by Thayer; notes and memoranda; newspaper clippings; and photographs of the Gaston Lachaise portrait bust of Thayer.
Thayer, Scofield, 1889-1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1987 with the assistance of the Beinecke Foundation and transferred to Beinecke Library in 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 5: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Dial/Scofield Thayer Papers YCAL MSS 34. Yale Collection of American Literature. Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
SCOFIELD THAYER (1889-1982)
Scofield Thayer was born in Worcester, Massachusetts in 1889 and educated at Milton Academy, Harvard College, and Oxford University. In 1919 Thayer and J. Sibley Watson purchased Dial magazine, which under their direction became perhaps the most important "little magazine" in the United States in the 1920s. Thayer withdrew from active participation in The Dial after a severe breakdown in 1926. He died in 1982.
For a fuller biography of Scofield Thayer, and a chronology for The Dial, see the register for YCAL MSS 34, Dial/Scofield Thayer Papers.
Scope and Contents
The Dial/Scofield Thayer Papers: Addition consists of four boxes of additional material to the Dial/Scofield Thayer Papers purchased in 1987. The Addition was transferred to the Beinecke Library in 1996. The papers span the dates 1885-1928, but the bulk of the material concerns the period 1915-1927. The papers are organized in two series. Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent; Series II, Personal Papers, alphabetically by type of material.
Correspondence consists almost entirely of letters sent to Thayer between 1926 and 1928, when he was hospitalized repeatedly following a mental breakdown. The writers, including Amy and Robert von Erdberg, Erik von Jurié, R. T. Nichol, Eleanor Schermerhorn, Ellen Thayer, and Lizzie Whittemore, send their wishes for improved health and sometimes detail plans for visits to MacLean Hospital. After one such visit, Amy von Erdberg wrote Thayer of her distress at seeing him hospitalized and offered to support his wish to be released. There are also two earlier letters from Thayer to his mother, Florence Thayer, and three third-party letters, two of which are to Florence Thayer also.
Series II, Personal Papers, includes bookplates, calling cards, newspaper clippings about America's entry into World War I, which Thayer opposed, and photographs. Folders 31-39 contain notes and memoranda kept by Thayer, often on small slips of paper, although some were apparently transcribed by a secretary at a later date. These cover a wide variety of subjects, including Thayer's family and friends, his marriage, his analyses by L. Pierce Clark and Sigmund Freud, aesthetic theory, and modern painting and literature.
Folders 23-25 contain correspondence and personal papers of Lucian Cary, including an income tax return for 1917 identifying him as a "journalist" and his wife, Augusta Cary, as executive secretary of the National Birth Control League. The return appears to be in Thayer's hand.
The section "School papers" includes versions of Thayer's Harvard Class Day essay on Dr. Faustus and several papers he read to literary societies at Oxford. "Writings" includes two poems, "Spleen anglais" and "Vienna," several essays, and a group of sketches and anecdotes about a figure named "Mercury" or "Mr. Mercury." At least some of the typescripts contained in the "Pending" file in "Writings of Others" may be by Thayer, who frequently employed pseudonyms when submitting work to The Dial.
Oversize material is located in Box 4 and consists of newspaper clippings and seven photographs of Gaston Lachaise's portrait bust of Thayer.
American literature -- 20th Century; Modernism (Literature); Publishers and publishing; Erdberg, Robert von; Jurié, Erik von; Nichol, R. T.; Thayer, Scofield, 1889-1982; Harvard University -- Class of 1913; Dial Magazine
- Correspondence, 1903-28; Series I; 0.25; (.5 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is alphabetically arranged by name of correspondent. Correspondence of others has been placed in the subseries Third- Party Correspondence, located at the end of the series, and alphabetically arranged by author.
  - THAYER CORRESPONDENCE
    - Arnold, Gertrude Weld, 1926 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Babbitt, Peter W., 1927 Dec 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Erdberg, Amy von, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      With photographs of the von Erdbergs and clippings
    - Erdberg, Robert von, 1927-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hotchkin Co., 1927 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jurié, Erik von, 1926 Jun 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Nichol, R. T., 1928 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - North, Ernest Dressel, 1927 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Schermerhorn, Eleanor, 1927 Oct 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Scofield, Myrtis (Mrs. William), 1925 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Scofield, William B., Jr., 1925, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Thayer, Ellen, 1928 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Thayer, Florence, 1914, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Whittall, Matthew Percival, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Whittemore, Lizzie B., 1927 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified, 1927 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Empty envelopes, 1903, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - THIRD-PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Lane, F. E. To Hermann P. Riccius, 1926 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      With copies of two articles by Scofield Thayer that appeared in the Milton Academy Orange and Blue
    - Richardson, Margery to Florence Thayer, 1913 Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Sheehan, Vesta Blake to Florence Thayer, n.y. Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Personal Papers, 1885-1927; Series II; 1.75; (3.5 boxes)
  Series II, Personal Papers is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Bookplates (with printing plate), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Calling cards and address slips (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cary, Lucian: papers, 1917-18, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
    Includes correspondence between Lucian Cary and Henry Ford's office; a letter to "Dear Bertie" signed "D. C." dated 18 Aug 1918; a request to French military censors for permission to publish an article in Collier's Weekly from Doris Cart; Liberty War Loan card and lapel pin; Cary's income tax return for 1917; and two unidentified photographs
  - Financial papers: inventory (Scofield family?), 1885-1907 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - World War I: Monroe Doctrine, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Oversize
    - World War I: Press conspiracy charges, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1917, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Notes and memoranda (Box 1, Folder 31-35)
  - Notes and memoranda (Box 2, Folder 36-39)
  - Photographs
    - Erdberg, Robert and Amy (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Thayer, Scofield: passport photos, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
      With notes and safety deposit box receipt dated 1928
    - Thayer, Scofield: portrait bust by Gaston Lachaise, n.d.
      See: Oversize
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Printed material
    - Dial magazine, Vol LXXVI, 5, 1924 May (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Dial magazine, Vol. LXXXIII, 2, 1927 Aug (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - School papers: Bancroft School
    - History themes, 1903 Feb (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - School papers: Harvard College
    - English 14: "Marlowe's Dr. Faustus," typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Greek 6: " Dr Faustus and Greek Tragedy," typescript (Box 2, Folder 47-48)
    - Harvard College Scholarship award, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "A Valentine (Pale regent of a thousand fragile dreams)," holograph and typescript (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - School papers: Oxford University
    - "Aesthetics" (paper read before an Oxford club, perhaps the Heretics), holograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51-52)
    - "Aristotle's Ethics," typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Compton Mackenzie" ("read before the Nineties Club of Oxford on June 11, 1915"), typescript (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Notebook on [the Novum Organum of?] Sir Francis Bacon, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Writings: Poems
    - "Spleen anglais," holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "Vienna," holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Writings: Prose
    - "Authority," holograph and typescript (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "Chicago," holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - "Dear Llewellyn," typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - "Done Into the English Tongue," typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Essay on Hugo Von Hofsmannthal, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Essay on English music, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - "Mercury--Literary Notes," holograph and typescript (Box 3, Folder 64-67)
    - "My Neighbor, Mr. Mercury": various sketches, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 68-69)
    - Review of the Harvard Monthly for January 1916, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 71-72)
  - Writings of Others
    - "By Lieut. Harold G. Peterson...," typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - "Pending" file: includes typescripts attributed to "B. Beasley," "Israel Solon," and a manuscript, "A College President Denounces the Voluntary System", [1917, n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 74-76)
- Oversize
  Oversize material has been placed here in series order.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1917, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Photographs: portrait bust of Thayer by Gaston Lachaise, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 78-84)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.4; (1 box)
  Box 5, Restricted Fragile Papers, contains fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 5: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 4 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Box 1, folder 6 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Box 1, folder 13 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Box 1, folder 23 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Box 1, folder 27 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Box 1, folder 28 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Box 1, folder 30 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Box 3, folder 58 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Box 3, folder 60 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Box 3, folder 62 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Box 3, folder 63 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Box 3, folder 64 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Box 3, folder 65 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Box 3, folder 66 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Box 3, folder 68 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Box 3, folder 69 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Box 3, folder 71 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Box 3, folder 76 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Box 4, folder 77 (Box 5, Folder 104)